Welcome to Dealmakers. I'm Sarah Sharp.
I'm a real attorney who helps people buy
and sell businesses every day. And I'm
going to talk to you about one of the
things that people miss in the diligence
process that really hurts their
transition. Um, it is very common to get
overwhelmed in the due diligence
process. If you're buying a business and
if you're selling, it's the same thing.
You're answering a bunch of questions.
It can be really tempting to start to
reduce those asks and not require so
much information because it's
exhausting. If there's one mistake that
any of my buyers make, it's that they
get too focused on the financials and
they say, "Let's just forget about the
rest because this is an asset purchase,
so it doesn't matter. I'll just swipe
the slate clean and we'll start with a
whole new company anyways, so none of
this is going to matter to me." And that
is a huge mistake. before I give you an
example or a few of things that you are
definitely missing in your diligence
process right now that are going to
really mess up your deal and your
transition. But before I get into it,
please subscribe if you find this
content valuable. And if you do like
this content, you'll love the courses at
dealacademy.org. We try to teach you how
to become the expert in running your
deal process. So, what are people
missing? It's all of the employment
stuff, including but not limited to
really good review of your seller's
employment handbook. I know that is not
the top of anyone's list. That's not
even on the diligence checklist of half
my clients, right? But here's one
instance that I ran across last week.
So, somebody wanted to buy a business
and the seller was a small company with
five employees. And this owner, she ran
a really sweet company. All five of the
employees were also female and young and
it was a great really energetic company.
The buyer was really excited. I said,
you know, hey, check out the employment
handbook. And so they sent it over to me
as a real lark. Like not even expecting
a review. But what I found in the
employment handbook is what almost every
lawyer who's ever reviewed an employment
handbook has found, which was, "Oh my
gosh, it's terrible. It's terrible.
Terrible." So what happens is people
think they need a handbook. They really
don't usually. um they think they need
an employment handbook and so they pull
one from a prior employer or they find
one on the internet and in doing so they
adopt a ton of laws that normally would
not apply to them and the things like
the FMLA, the ADA, all kinds of rules
that apply to folks with 50 or more or
15 or more employees. They have five,
but they've now just adopted these huge
laws and made them by virtue of putting
them in their handbook and saying that
they'll comply with them. Made their
small business required to be compliant
with these big rules. So, that is not
good for the target. Sure. But how does
it impact the buyer, right? Let's assume
it's an asset purchase. Well, does it
matter? I mean, yeah, it was a bad
handbook, but that's a small thing,
right? Let's focus on the big things
like the debt service coverage ratio and
how much profit we're going to make
right after closing. But here's the
reason that you read it. Five employee
business has a handbook that I open up
and it's 70 pages long. There is nothing
that can be in there that is good.
There's lots of liability exposure for
things like dress code which is going to
have lots of really risky stuff in
there. a lot of risky requirements
related to vacation approval, PTO,
things where there's I mean, if there's
70 pages, you're almost truly you're
breaking some rules by what you're
saying if you're a small business,
right? Unless you have 50 states or
something that you're trying to comply
with. So, I immediately get nervous and
start control finding for the different
things that an employee handbook might
have. And what we learned is no one
really understood it, but for whatever
reason, they adopted the FMLA. and the
FMLA specifically relating to what they
termed in this handbook maternity leave
policies, what I would call parental
leave. So all five of their young female
employees had been guaranteed 12 weeks
paid and maternity leave, which is fine
if it's on purpose. You know, it's even
good if it's on purpose, but the seller
didn't even know that they had that
policy in there. And I'm pretty sure
being a woman and mother myself, those
five employees knew it was in there cuz
that is pretty much the number one thing
that we're going to be looking for, but
not necessarily openly discussing as a
woman in the workplace. So then you have
five employees who all are on the
forefront of their childbearing plans
who are being bought by an owner who
then has to decide, you know, am I going
to match this term which is a real
financial commitment or am I going to
tell the employees, hey, you can have 12
weeks unpaid maternity leave perhaps and
you can use your PTO for it and deal
with of fallout that relates to that.
And as you can imagine, it did result in
some really tricky negotiations because
the buyer wasn't permitted to meet with
the seller's employees prior to closing.
So then the buyer has to make a plan for
matching the 12 weeks paid promise that
was buried in that 70page employment
handbook uh for five employees and then
probably every employee hired
thereafter. So, that's a normal smallish
thing, but can really tank your
transition plans because if you don't
offer it, your employees leave. And if
you do offer it, your financial
projections need to look a little bit
different, right? Especially since a lot
of that can overlap. And in this case,
we're talking about, you know, something
that's seasonal. So, it could hit at a
very high traffic, high demand time. And
then the buyer needs to be in a position
where they can make sure that they have
coverage for that and that they can
continue to offer such a generous for a
small business type of policy to future
employees. So most of my buyers don't go
so far as to review the employment
handbook, the target business that
they're looking for. And that's one of
many things that they might be missing
by doing that. if they had not seen
would have certainly scuttled their
attempts to acquire the business. But
because they did see it on the front
end, they were in a position where they
could renegotiate terms with the seller
to make it something that wouldn't
totally destroy their business after
closing. If you found this very, very
nuanced video valuable at all, please
leave a comment, share this channel with
friends, like and subscribe, and check
out dealacademy.org. Boy.